<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Untitled RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>site-lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Untitled RSS Feed</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 07:13:14 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="site-lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 07:13:12 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[URBANISM - Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="On the Planning of Cities" data-href="On the Planning of Cities" href="99-on-the-planning-of-cities/on-the-planning-of-cities.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">HOME</a>Urbanism is about living in close proximity and the consequences this has for us.What, in truth, is a city?Urbanism starts from a simple decision: people opt to live side by side, packed into large, dense, long-lasting clusters made up mostly of strangers.<br>A well-known sociological definition portrays a city as “a relatively large, dense, and permanent settlement of socially heterogeneous individuals”.<a data-footref="[inline0" href="#fn-1-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[1]</a> Put bluntly, it means many people crammed into a single location, mostly unrelated to one another, sharing life side by side over long periods.<br>There is also a second, equally important way to think about a city. Rather than focusing solely on who happens to live within its bounds, we can focus on what it does for the wider region around it. Seen this way, a city is a settlement that carries out specialised functions — administration, storage, trade, craft production, religious and political leadership — on behalf of a much larger surrounding countryside.<a data-footref="[inline1" href="#fn-2-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[2]</a> It acts as a service node for farms, villages, and smaller towns.Urbanism, as an idea, lies at the junction of these two perspectives. It is about more than simply having “big settlements”. It is a particular way of organising human life: density plus specialisation. It means many people in one place, doing different kinds of work, linked through institutions that extend beyond the city walls.Once this pattern takes hold, it alters almost everything: how food is produced, how power is exercised, how diseases spread, how wealth builds up, and how we think about time, identity, and the future. Urbanism is not merely scenery in the background. It is one of humanity’s primary technologies for reorganising society.The first cities can be seen as slow, long-running experiments in living at high density.<br>The earliest well-documented urban system emerges in southern Mesopotamia, in what archaeologists refer to as the Uruk Period, roughly 4200–3100 BCE.<a data-footref="[inline2" href="#fn-3-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[3]</a> Cities such as Ur did not erupt into existence overnight. The shift from villages to fully urban societies unfolded over roughly 500–700 years.<a data-footref="[inline3" href="#fn-4-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[4]</a> That represents many generations of people learning how to inhabit new kinds of spaces under new rules.<br>Archaeological surveys indicate that early Mesopotamian cities typically expanded by spreading out from an older village core, maintaining roughly similar densities as they grew.<a data-footref="[inline4" href="#fn-5-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[5]</a> Ur itself covered about 10 hectares around 3800 BCE and grew to roughly 15 hectares by about 3200 BCE.<a data-footref="[inline5" href="#fn-6-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[6]</a> By modern standards that may seem modest, but in its own time it marked a dramatic concentration of people, resources, and decision-making.<br>Mesopotamia is just one case among many. Cities arose independently in other regions — the Indus Valley, northern China, Mesoamerica, the Andes — following different local pathways but converging on strikingly similar outcomes: dense populations, long-distance networks, specialised labour, and formal institutions.<a data-footref="[inline6" href="#fn-7-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[7]</a><br>The physical constraints of each region left a deep imprint on its urban form. In Mesopotamia, cities were strung along rivers and canals that enabled bulk transport of grain, building materials, and goods.<a data-footref="[inline7" href="#fn-8-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[8]</a> In central Mexico, cities such as Teotihuacan lacked large domestic animals for carrying loads and had no convenient river routes for boats. They therefore had to construct entire urban and imperial systems around human porters and walking.<a data-footref="[inline8" href="#fn-9-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[9]</a> That logistical difference helped shape street plans, storage systems, and even the practical upper limits of city size.So from the outset, urbanism is not a single, uniform phenomenon. It is a family of solutions to a common problem: how to concentrate people and power in a given landscape, using whatever transport, crops, and animals happen to be available.Why, then, do cities form at all, and what do surplus, safety, and pressure have to do with it?If for most of history the majority of people were farmers, why did some communities decide to crowd into places where most residents did not grow their own food?The short answer is: surplus. The longer answer is: surplus combined with pressure.<br>First, consider surplus. Large-scale urban life is impossible without a farming system that routinely produces more food than local farmers themselves consume, and that can channel that surplus into town. In the ancient Near East, the domestication of cereals such as wheat and barley, along with herd animals, generated this extra margin. It allowed a portion of the population to be released from direct food production and to specialise in crafts, administration, religious roles, and trade.<a data-footref="[inline9" href="#fn-10-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[10]</a><br>Urbanisation, in turn, feeds back into the countryside. As people relocate into cities, fewer farmers remain in rural areas; the land they leave tends to be consolidated into larger farms.<a data-footref="[inline10" href="#fn-11-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[11]</a> In many settings, larger farm sizes are associated with higher productivity per worker. Urban demand also pushes farmers towards more intensive cultivation: manuring fields more heavily and concentrating on high-yield, high-demand crops, such as the barley used for beer in ancient Mesopotamian cities.<a data-footref="[inline11" href="#fn-12-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[12]</a> Urbanism, seen this way, is a system-wide optimisation: it rearranges labour so that both fields and workshops are used more intensively.Surplus on its own does not explain why people submit to new forms of rule or accept the risks that come with dense living. Here, historians and economists propose several mechanisms.<br>In one account, elites gradually tighten their grip on the best farmland as population grows and technology advances. As common fields contract and wages fall, ordinary farmers are nudged or driven into non-farm work in emerging towns and cities — especially when openings in urban manufacturing look more appealing than deteriorating conditions in the countryside.<a data-footref="[inline12" href="#fn-13-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[13]</a><br>In another account, warfare among elites is the main engine. When conflict over land and tribute intensifies, retreating behind city walls becomes a rational act of self-defence. Populations cluster in fortified locations, both to shield themselves and to underpin elite military ventures. Victorious warlords then use these dense centres as bases for territorial expansion.<a data-footref="[inline13" href="#fn-14-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[14]</a><br>A third pathway emphasises the environment. When climate or geography funnels people into narrow zones — river valleys, oases, coastal plains — populations become denser almost by compulsion. Land grows more valuable, wages for ordinary workers decline, and elites who control access to these safe or fertile zones gain leverage. Under these squeezed conditions, urbanisation and state formation follow.<a data-footref="[inline14" href="#fn-15-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[15]</a>Across these accounts, one idea recurs: cities arise when the organisational benefits of crowding — for farming, warfare, or resource control — exceed the obvious discomforts of living packed together.Cities can also be understood as dense machines for running institutions.Once dense, diverse populations are concentrated in one place, new kinds of rules, records, rituals, and buildings are needed to keep everything functioning. This is the institutional dimension of urbanism.<br>Early cities functioned as “clearing houses” for resources.<a data-footref="[inline15" href="#fn-16-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[16]</a> Grain, textiles, tribute, and craft goods were brought into central storehouses, redistributed to workers, soldiers, and priests, and channelled into monuments and public works. The closer workshops, offices, and storage rooms sat to one another, the lower the logistical costs: information and goods could move quickly through a compact space.<br>To manage all this, societies had to invent or greatly expand administrative tools: accounting systems, legal codes, standardised weights and measures, professional scribes, permanent offices, layered hierarchies. Social complexity increased through diversification (more specialised roles), connectivity (denser ties between them), and standardisation (shared rules and categories).<a data-footref="[inline16" href="#fn-17-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[17]</a><br>Urban layouts mirrored these changes. In Mesopotamia, temple and palace complexes dominated city centres, physically embodying the union of religious, economic, and political authority.<a data-footref="[inline17" href="#fn-18-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[18]</a> In many settings, priest-kings or other elites legitimised their power through religious narratives and rituals. Early sociologists, and later Max Weber, argued that cities are moulded not only by material needs but also by worldviews: ideas about gods, justice, purity, and order seep into street plans and law codes.<a data-footref="[inline18" href="#fn-19-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[19]</a>Urbanism, then, is not simply about physical proximity. It concerns new forms of coordination — bureaucratic, religious, legal — that only make sense when many thousands of people must share space and resources day after day.High density brings greater output, but that extra production is shared very unevenly.<br>Recent work on both ancient and modern cities highlights a key point: urban systems tend to produce more than the sum of their parts. The larger and denser a settlement becomes, the more interactions each person experiences, and the more ideas, deals, and collaborations can be generated per head. Statistically, socio-economic output increases faster than population size.<a data-footref="[inline19" href="#fn-20-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[20]</a><br>Researchers refer to this as “increasing returns to scale”. In mathematical models, it appears as a scaling exponent greater than one: double the population and you obtain more than double the output.<a data-footref="[inline20" href="#fn-21-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[21]</a> This pattern surfaces not only in modern GDP statistics but also in archaeological proxies.<br>In ancient cities of the Basin of Mexico, the volume of public monuments — pyramids, plazas, ceremonial platforms — increases superlinearly with estimated population size. The bigger the city, the more monument-building per person it was able to sustain.<a data-footref="[inline21" href="#fn-22-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[22]</a> Household sizes, inferred from the area of house mounds, also tend to be larger in more populous settlements, suggesting higher average productivity or access to resources for residents of big cities.<a data-footref="[inline22" href="#fn-23-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[23]</a><br>Yet these gains are not shared evenly. The same studies reveal substantial inequality in how built space is distributed. In the pre-Hispanic Basin of Mexico, the top 10 percent of households ended up occupying 40–50 percent of total housing area.<a data-footref="[inline23" href="#fn-24-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[24]</a> That skewed pattern is the physical imprint of unequal access to the benefits of density.Put simply, cities are engines that convert dense social networks into extra output. But they also direct a disproportionate share of that extra output to people already well positioned inside those networks — politically, economically, or spatially.High productivity has long come with a biological price tag: the urban graveyard.If cities are so productive, why were they, for much of history, such hostile places for human bodies?<br>Bioarchaeology, the study of human remains in archaeological contexts, presents a stark picture. Early and medieval cities frequently endured very high mortality rates. Diseases spread rapidly in crowded streets, water sources became contaminated, and waste disposal was poor. The so-called “Urban Graveyard Effect” captures this reality: cities tended to function as demographic sinks, where deaths outnumbered births over the long term.<a data-footref="[inline24" href="#fn-25-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[25]</a><br>For cities to persist, they had to draw in people continuously from the countryside. Rural migrants took the place of those lost to disease and hardship. The fact that urban systems endured despite this constant human loss tells us something important: the strategic advantages of the city — for rulers, armies, merchants, and sometimes ordinary people seeking protection or opportunity — outweighed its biological dangers.<a data-footref="[inline25" href="#fn-26-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[26]</a><br>Specific health problems show up clearly in skeletal remains. Studies of medieval urban populations in places such as Croatia reveal widespread malnutrition and vitamin deficiencies, consistent with diets lacking fresh fruits and vegetables.<a data-footref="[inline26" href="#fn-27-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[27]</a> Overcrowding and poor sanitation created ideal conditions for parasites and infectious diseases. Archaeologists find signs of anaemia, chronic infections, arthritis from hard physical labour, tuberculosis, and sexually transmitted diseases such as syphilis in these urban remains.<a data-footref="[inline27" href="#fn-28-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[28]</a>Urbanism, especially before modern public health and infrastructure, meant participating in a system that was extraordinarily productive yet physically risky. It was a trade-off: security, access, and opportunity in exchange for higher odds of sickness and early death.Modern cities follow old logics but wield new tools.Modern urbanism looks very different on the surface — glass towers, highways, digital networks — yet many of its underlying mechanisms remain surprisingly similar.<br>Economists examining contemporary metropolitan areas find that higher employment density, and the dominance of a “primary” city in a region, are strongly associated with higher worker productivity.<a data-footref="[inline28" href="#fn-29-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[29]</a> Firms and workers benefit from being close: information travels faster, specialised services cluster together, and labour markets are deeper and more flexible. Congested freeways and overcrowded trains are often symptoms of underlying economic strength, not merely planning failures.<a data-footref="[inline29" href="#fn-30-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[30]</a><br>The COVID-19 pandemic created a natural experiment in what happens when physical density is stripped away from knowledge-intensive work. One detailed study of more than 10,000 information technology professionals found that working from home was linked to an 8–19 percent drop in productivity.<a data-footref="[inline30" href="#fn-31-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[31]</a> The main cause was not laziness or distraction but higher communication costs: more time spent coordinating, more meetings, and fewer uninterrupted blocks of focused work.<a data-footref="[inline31" href="#fn-32-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[32]</a>This modern evidence echoes the ancient pattern: density behaves like a kind of “network lubricant”. It reduces the friction involved in organising many people to carry out complex tasks together. Remove that density and the hidden costs of coordination suddenly show up as visible and measurable.Today, demography and money together determine who keeps the city running.In ancient times, cities required a steady flow of rural migrants simply to stay alive biologically. Today, in many richer countries, the challenge is less about sheer headcount and more about maintaining a viable tax and income base.<br>Demographic studies show that the relationship between density and population growth is far from simple. In Mediterranean Europe, for example, rapid growth in the mid-20th century was concentrated in major metropolitan centres such as Athens. By the early 2000s, however, growth had shifted towards medium-sized cities and some accessible rural regions.<a data-footref="[inline32" href="#fn-33-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[33]</a> As some big cities near the limits of their appeal or affordability, their surrounding networks adjust.<br>At the same time, cities must fund infrastructure, schools, healthcare, and the long-term promises they have made — pensions, debt servicing, maintenance of ageing systems. To achieve this, they depend heavily on tax revenue from residents and businesses. Research from the United States emphasises how important it is for cities to maintain either a large population with solid midrange incomes or a smaller population that includes a sizeable share of high-income households.<a data-footref="[inline33" href="#fn-34-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[34]</a> Young, well-educated adults are particularly valued because they are both economically productive and demographically “renewing”.<a data-footref="[inline34" href="#fn-35-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[35]</a>So the modern city has shifted from needing a constant influx of bodies to requiring a constant influx of income. The former demographic sink has, in many places, turned into a fiscal sink: a system that can remain stable only if new flows of money and high-earning residents keep arriving.On a largely urban planet, cities act as powerful environmental engines.<br>Today, most humans live in cities or urbanised regions. This means the environment that matters most for day-to-day life is no longer a forest, desert, or open field. Instead, it is the built environment: streets, buildings, pipes, cables, and air thickened by exhaust and noise.<a data-footref="[inline35" href="#fn-36-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[36]</a><br>From an ecological point of view, cities are net consumers. They import food, water, energy, and materials from vast hinterlands, process and use them, and then export waste and pollution. The result is a concentrated pattern of environmental stress: heat islands, poor air quality, noise, lack of green space, and high energy demand.<a data-footref="[inline36" href="#fn-37-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[37]</a><br>To manage these pressures, planners and scientists have assembled a battery of metrics. For the built environment, they measure noise levels, healthcare space per person, recreational and green space per person, and more.<a data-footref="[inline37" href="#fn-38-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[38]</a> For the physical environment, they track air quality indices, satellite-based vegetation indices such as NDVI, and land surface temperature to map where cities are hottest.<a data-footref="[inline38" href="#fn-39-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[39]</a><br>Because these factors intersect in messy ways, researchers turn to advanced analytical methods. Fuzzy inference systems, for example, are used to combine multiple imperfect indicators — pollution levels, weather data, health records — into estimates of health risks for city residents.<a data-footref="[inline39" href="#fn-40-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[40]</a> The details are technical, but the logic is simple: when millions of people are exposed to overlapping environmental hazards, you need good tools for predicting where harm will be greatest and which interventions will help most.Urbanism, at this planetary scale, becomes a central driver of climate change and biodiversity loss — but it is also a potential platform for concentrated solutions, because changing policies in a handful of large cities can rapidly affect the daily lives of tens of millions.Contemporary cities sit in vast networks even as they are riven by internal splits.Modern cities do not stand alone in their landscapes. They function as nodes in enormous networks: trade flows, financial circuits, migration routes, data cables, and governance bodies.<br>In global climate politics, for instance, cities operate within transnational networks that cut across nation-states. Some cities assume “challenger” roles, pushing for more ambitious climate goals than their national governments. Others act as “facilitators”, spreading best practices and coordinating across regions.<a data-footref="[inline40" href="#fn-41-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[41]</a> Scholars of global governance now treat cities as key actors in their own right, not merely local shells filled by national policy.<a data-footref="[inline41" href="#fn-42-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[42]</a><br>Within their own boundaries, however, cities remain sharply divided. The very urban regions that concentrate innovation, literacy, and high incomes also concentrate hardship. Comfortable neighbourhoods with good schools and safe streets can sit alongside districts marked by unstable housing, unemployment, and high crime.<a data-footref="[inline42" href="#fn-43-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[43]</a> This spatial polarisation is another face of the unequal distribution of density’s benefits.<br>To understand and manage these differences, researchers deploy spatial statistics. Techniques such as the Getis–Ord Gi index identify clusters of “hot” and “cold” spots — areas with especially high or low resilience, income, or service provision. The Theil index and related measures quantify how unequally resilience or development is distributed among neighbourhoods.<a data-footref="[inline43" href="#fn-44-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[44]</a> These tools assign numbers to what city residents often sense intuitively: not all districts have the same capacity to absorb shocks or to adapt.Urbanism, viewed through this lens, is always double: cities are at once engines of global co-ordination and local inequality, hubs of cooperation and sites of sharp internal division.Urbanism can be seen as a 6,000-year-old bargain.Across six millennia, from Uruk to today’s megacities, the basic bargain of urbanism has stayed strikingly stable.<br>Functionally, cities exist to shorten distances within dense social networks. By packing people together, they make it easier to specialise, trade, co-ordinate, and organise defence.<a data-footref="[inline44" href="#fn-45-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[45]</a> Mathematically, they convert that closeness into increasing returns: larger, denser cities tend to produce disproportionately more economic and cultural output than smaller, sparser ones, a pattern visible both in ancient monument volumes and in modern GDP statistics.<a data-footref="[inline45" href="#fn-46-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[46]</a><br>Yet density brings challenges that must be managed: conflict, inequality, disease, environmental strain. Urban societies have responded by building complex institutions — states, bureaucracies, religious systems, legal orders — capable of handling large, heterogeneous populations.<a data-footref="[inline46" href="#fn-47-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[47]</a> Successful cities, ancient and modern, often mix centralised authority with flexible, overlapping networks of power and cooperation, rather than relying on rigid top-down planning alone.<a data-footref="[inline47" href="#fn-48-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[48]</a><br>In return for their non-linear gains in productivity and possibility, cities pay in other currencies: higher base levels of inequality, chronic pressure on public health, heightened environmental impacts, and a structural need for continuing inflows — once of human lives, now of income and investment.<a data-footref="[inline48" href="#fn-49-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[49]</a>Urbanism, in this sense, is not a passing phase but a long-running human strategy. It is how our species has chosen, again and again, to solve the problem of organising many people in limited space — and to accept the costs of density in order to harvest its extraordinary benefits.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="URBANISM - Density Machines - Comparative Urban Forms and Metabolisms" data-href="URBANISM - Density Machines - Comparative Urban Forms and Metabolisms" href="99-on-the-planning-of-cities/urbanism-density-machines-comparative-urban-forms-and-metabolisms.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Density Machines</a> <br>The Archaeology of Early Cities: “What Is the City but the People ..., accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.annualreviews.org/content/journals/10.1146/annurev-anthro-041222-094823?crawler=true" target="_self">https://www.annualreviews.org/content/journals/10.1146/annurev-anthro-041222-094823?crawler=true</a><a href="#fnref-1-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Archaeology of Early Cities: “What Is the City but the People?” - Annual Reviews, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.annualreviews.org/content/journals/10.1146/annurev-anthro-041222-094823?crawler=true&amp;mimetype=application/pdf" target="_self">https://www.annualreviews.org/content/journals/10.1146/annurev-anthro-041222-094823?crawler=true&amp;mimetype=application/pdf</a><a href="#fnref-2-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Suburbs of the Early Mesopotamian City of Ur (Tell al-Muqayyar, Iraq) | American Journal of Archaeology: Vol 127, No 4, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/725907" target="_self">https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/725907</a><a href="#fnref-3-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Uruk Mesopotamia and Its Neighbors: Cross-Cultural Interactions in the Era of State Formation | Request PDF - ResearchGate, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/284463179_Uruk_Mesopotamia_and_Its_Neighbors_Cross-Cultural_Interactions_in_the_Era_of_State_Formation" target="_self">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/284463179_Uruk_Mesopotamia_and_Its_Neighbors_Cross-Cultural_Interactions_in_the_Era_of_State_Formation</a><a href="#fnref-4-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Early urban development in the Near East - PubMed, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17761874/" target="_self">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17761874/</a><a href="#fnref-5-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Suburbs of the Early Mesopotamian City of Ur (Tell al-Muqayyar, Iraq) | American Journal of Archaeology: Vol 127, No 4, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/725907" target="_self">https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/725907</a><a href="#fnref-6-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Emergence of Cities and States (Chapter 11) - Economic Prehistory, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/economic-prehistory/emergence-of-cities-and-states/8AE2A355AAFBFF8055F72DC65E0AB358" target="_self">https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/economic-prehistory/emergence-of-cities-and-states/8AE2A355AAFBFF8055F72DC65E0AB358</a><a href="#fnref-7-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Archaeology of Early Cities: “What Is the City but the People?” - Annual Reviews, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.annualreviews.org/content/journals/10.1146/annurev-anthro-041222-094823?crawler=true&amp;mimetype=application/pdf" target="_self">https://www.annualreviews.org/content/journals/10.1146/annurev-anthro-041222-094823?crawler=true&amp;mimetype=application/pdf</a><a href="#fnref-8-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Full article: Bridging prehistory and history in the archaeology of cities, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1179/2042458215Y.00000000019" target="_self">https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1179/2042458215Y.00000000019</a><a href="#fnref-9-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Consequences of Agriculture in Mesopotamia, Anatolia, and the Levant | Oxford Research Encyclopedia of Environmental Science, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://oxfordre.com/environmentalscience/view/10.1093/acrefore/9780199389414.001.0001/acrefore-9780199389414-e-167" target="_self">https://oxfordre.com/environmentalscience/view/10.1093/acrefore/9780199389414.001.0001/acrefore-9780199389414-e-167</a><a href="#fnref-10-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Urbanisation and rural development in developing countries: a review of pathways and impacts, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.idos-research.de/uploads/media/DP_5.2022.pdf" target="_self">https://www.idos-research.de/uploads/media/DP_5.2022.pdf</a><a href="#fnref-11-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Urban form and scale shaped the agroecology of early 'cities' in northern Mesopotamia, the Aegean and Central Europe, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC9580239/" target="_self">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC9580239/</a><a href="#fnref-12-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Emergence of Cities and States (Chapter 11) - Economic Prehistory, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/economic-prehistory/emergence-of-cities-and-states/8AE2A355AAFBFF8055F72DC65E0AB358" target="_self">https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/economic-prehistory/emergence-of-cities-and-states/8AE2A355AAFBFF8055F72DC65E0AB358</a><a href="#fnref-13-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Emergence of Cities and States (Chapter 11) - Economic Prehistory, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/economic-prehistory/emergence-of-cities-and-states/8AE2A355AAFBFF8055F72DC65E0AB358" target="_self">https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/economic-prehistory/emergence-of-cities-and-states/8AE2A355AAFBFF8055F72DC65E0AB358</a>; Investigating the origins of mesopotamian civilization - PubMed, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17757228/" target="_self">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17757228/</a><a href="#fnref-14-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Emergence of Cities and States (Chapter 11) - Economic Prehistory, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/economic-prehistory/emergence-of-cities-and-states/8AE2A355AAFBFF8055F72DC65E0AB358" target="_self">https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/economic-prehistory/emergence-of-cities-and-states/8AE2A355AAFBFF8055F72DC65E0AB358</a><a href="#fnref-15-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Investigating the origins of mesopotamian civilization - PubMed, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17757228/" target="_self">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17757228/</a><a href="#fnref-16-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>On complex archaeologies: conceptualizing social complexity and its potential for archaeology - ResearchGate, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/330816032_On_complex_archaeologies_conceptualizing_social_complexity_and_its_potential_for_archaeology" target="_self">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/330816032_On_complex_archaeologies_conceptualizing_social_complexity_and_its_potential_for_archaeology</a><a href="#fnref-17-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Settlements and Social Structure in the Ancient World | Research Starters - EBSCO, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.ebsco.com/research-starters/history/settlements-and-social-structure-ancient-world" target="_self">https://www.ebsco.com/research-starters/history/settlements-and-social-structure-ancient-world</a><a href="#fnref-18-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Introduction: a history of the study of early cities (Chapter 1) - Cambridge University Press, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/cambridge-world-history/introduction-a-history-of-the-study-of-early-cities/DA9614DE218944E42D2AA470A859849D" target="_self">https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/cambridge-world-history/introduction-a-history-of-the-study-of-early-cities/DA9614DE218944E42D2AA470A859849D</a><a href="#fnref-19-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>(PDF) Settlement Scaling and Increasing Returns in an Ancient Society - ResearchGate, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/273003184_Settlement_Scaling_and_Increasing_Returns_in_an_Ancient_Society" target="_self">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/273003184_Settlement_Scaling_and_Increasing_Returns_in_an_Ancient_Society</a><a href="#fnref-20-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Settlement Scaling and Increasing Returns in an Ancient Society - Santa Fe Institute, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.santafe.edu/research/results/working-papers/settlement-scaling-and-increasing-returns-in-an-an" target="_self">https://www.santafe.edu/research/results/working-papers/settlement-scaling-and-increasing-returns-in-an-an</a><a href="#fnref-21-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>(PDF) Settlement Scaling and Increasing Returns in an Ancient Society - ResearchGate, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/273003184_Settlement_Scaling_and_Increasing_Returns_in_an_Ancient_Society" target="_self">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/273003184_Settlement_Scaling_and_Increasing_Returns_in_an_Ancient_Society</a><a href="#fnref-22-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>(PDF) Settlement Scaling and Increasing Returns in an Ancient Society - ResearchGate, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/273003184_Settlement_Scaling_and_Increasing_Returns_in_an_Ancient_Society" target="_self">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/273003184_Settlement_Scaling_and_Increasing_Returns_in_an_Ancient_Society</a><a href="#fnref-23-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Studies of Ancient Cities Suggest We Should Abandon Planning Elites | Smart Cities Dive, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.smartcitiesdive.com/ex/sustainablecitiescollective/how-ancient-and-modern-cities-compare-and-why-planners-should-care/1053391/" target="_self">https://www.smartcitiesdive.com/ex/sustainablecitiescollective/how-ancient-and-modern-cities-compare-and-why-planners-should-care/1053391/</a><a href="#fnref-24-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Toward a bioarchaeology of urbanization: Demography, health, and behavior in cities in the past - ResearchGate, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/349523083_Toward_a_bioarchaeology_of_urbanization_Demography_health_and_behavior_in_cities_in_the_past" target="_self">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/349523083_Toward_a_bioarchaeology_of_urbanization_Demography_health_and_behavior_in_cities_in_the_past</a><a href="#fnref-25-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Investigating the origins of mesopotamian civilization - PubMed, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17757228/" target="_self">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17757228/</a><a href="#fnref-26-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Health Risks Associated With Medieval Urban Living - Examples from Croatia, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/325619806_Health_Risks_Associated_With_Medieval_Urban_Living_-" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/325619806_Health_Risks_Associated_With_Medieval_Urban_Living_-" target="_self">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/325619806<em></em>-</a>Health_Risks_Associated_With_Medieval_Urban_Living*Examples_from_Croatia<a href="#fnref-27-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Health Risks Associated With Medieval Urban Living - Examples from Croatia, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/325619806_Health_Risks_Associated_With_Medieval_Urban_Living" target="_self">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/325619806_Health_Risks_Associated_With_Medieval_Urban_Living</a>*-_Examples_from_Croatia<a href="#fnref-28-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Efficient Urbanisation: Economic Performance and the Shape of the Metropolis - Rebalance, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://rebalancemobility.eu/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/ContentServer-1.pdf" target="_self">https://rebalancemobility.eu/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/ContentServer-1.pdf</a><a href="#fnref-29-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Efficient Urbanisation: Economic Performance and the Shape of the Metropolis - Rebalance, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://rebalancemobility.eu/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/ContentServer-1.pdf" target="_self">https://rebalancemobility.eu/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/ContentServer-1.pdf</a><a href="#fnref-30-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Work from Home and Productivity: Evidence from Personnel and Analytics Data on Information Technology Professionals | Journal of Political Economy Microeconomics, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/721803" target="_self">https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/721803</a><a href="#fnref-31-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Work from Home and Productivity: Evidence from Personnel and Analytics Data on Information Technology Professionals | Journal of Political Economy Microeconomics, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/721803" target="_self">https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/721803</a><a href="#fnref-32-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Population Trends and Urbanization: Simulating Density Effects Using a Local Regression Approach - MDPI, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.mdpi.com/2220-9964/9/7/454" target="_self">https://www.mdpi.com/2220-9964/9/7/454</a><a href="#fnref-33-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Population, Migration, and Generations in Urban Neighborhoods, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.clevelandfed.org/publications/economic-commentary/2019/ec-201908-population-migration-and-generations-in-urban-neighborhoods" target="_self">https://www.clevelandfed.org/publications/economic-commentary/2019/ec-201908-population-migration-and-generations-in-urban-neighborhoods</a><a href="#fnref-34-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Population, Migration, and Generations in Urban Neighborhoods, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.clevelandfed.org/publications/economic-commentary/2019/ec-201908-population-migration-and-generations-in-urban-neighborhoods" target="_self">https://www.clevelandfed.org/publications/economic-commentary/2019/ec-201908-population-migration-and-generations-in-urban-neighborhoods</a><a href="#fnref-35-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>(PDF) Urban sustainability and urban form metrics - ResearchGate, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/284224792_Urban_sustainability_and_urban_form_metrics" target="_self">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/284224792_Urban_sustainability_and_urban_form_metrics</a><a href="#fnref-36-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>(PDF) Urban sustainability and urban form metrics - ResearchGate, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/284224792_Urban_sustainability_and_urban_form_metrics" target="_self">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/284224792_Urban_sustainability_and_urban_form_metrics</a><a href="#fnref-37-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Evaluating urban environmental quality using multi criteria decision making - PMC, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10845730/" target="_self">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10845730/</a><a href="#fnref-38-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Evaluating urban environmental quality using multi criteria decision making - PMC, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10845730/" target="_self">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10845730/</a><a href="#fnref-39-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Urban environmental monitoring and health risk assessment introducing a fuzzy intelligent computing model - PMC - NIH, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC11188348/" target="_self">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC11188348/</a><a href="#fnref-40-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Role of Cities in Global Climate Governance - Lund University Publications, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://lup.lub.lu.se/luur/download?func=downloadFile&amp;recordOId=8997737&amp;fileOId=8997741" target="_self">https://lup.lub.lu.se/luur/download?func=downloadFile&amp;recordOId=8997737&amp;fileOId=8997741</a><a href="#fnref-41-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Redalyc. FROM CITY-STATES TO GLOBAL CITIES: THE ROLE OF CITIES IN GLOBAL GOVERNANCE, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.redalyc.org/pdf/4135/413553386002.pdf" target="_self">https://www.redalyc.org/pdf/4135/413553386002.pdf</a><a href="#fnref-42-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Redalyc. FROM CITY-STATES TO GLOBAL CITIES: THE ROLE OF CITIES IN GLOBAL GOVERNANCE, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.redalyc.org/pdf/4135/413553386002.pdf" target="_self">https://www.redalyc.org/pdf/4135/413553386002.pdf</a><a href="#fnref-43-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Differences and Drivers of Urban Resilience in Eight Major Urban Agglomerations: Evidence from China - MDPI, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-445X/11/9/1470" target="_self">https://www.mdpi.com/2073-445X/11/9/1470</a><a href="#fnref-44-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Emergence of Cities and States (Chapter 11) - Economic Prehistory, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/economic-prehistory/emergence-of-cities-and-states/8AE2A355AAFBFF8055F72DC65E0AB358" target="_self">https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/economic-prehistory/emergence-of-cities-and-states/8AE2A355AAFBFF8055F72DC65E0AB358</a><a href="#fnref-45-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Settlement Scaling and Increasing Returns in an Ancient Society - Santa Fe Institute, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.santafe.edu/research/results/working-papers/settlement-scaling-and-increasing-returns-in-an-an" target="_self">https://www.santafe.edu/research/results/working-papers/settlement-scaling-and-increasing-returns-in-an-an</a><a href="#fnref-46-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Emergence of Cities and States (Chapter 11) - Economic Prehistory, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/economic-prehistory/emergence-of-cities-and-states/8AE2A355AAFBFF8055F72DC65E0AB358" target="_self">https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/economic-prehistory/emergence-of-cities-and-states/8AE2A355AAFBFF8055F72DC65E0AB358</a><a href="#fnref-47-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Studies of Ancient Cities Suggest We Should Abandon Planning Elites | Smart Cities Dive, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.smartcitiesdive.com/ex/sustainablecitiescollective/how-ancient-and-modern-cities-compare-and-why-planners-should-care/1053391/" target="_self">https://www.smartcitiesdive.com/ex/sustainablecitiescollective/how-ancient-and-modern-cities-compare-and-why-planners-should-care/1053391/</a><a href="#fnref-48-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Toward a bioarchaeology of urbanization: Demography, health, and behavior in cities in the past - ResearchGate, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/349523083_Toward_a_bioarchaeology_of_urbanization_Demography_health_and_behavior_in_cities_in_the_past" target="_self">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/349523083_Toward_a_bioarchaeology_of_urbanization_Demography_health_and_behavior_in_cities_in_the_past</a>; Population, Migration, and Generations in Urban Neighborhoods, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.clevelandfed.org/publications/economic-commentary/2019/ec-201908-population-migration-and-generations-in-urban-neighborhoods" target="_self">https://www.clevelandfed.org/publications/economic-commentary/2019/ec-201908-population-migration-and-generations-in-urban-neighborhoods</a>; Evaluating urban environmental quality using multi criteria decision making - PMC, accessed on November 29, 2025, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10845730/" target="_self">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10845730/</a><a href="#fnref-49-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
]]></description><link>99-on-the-planning-of-cities/urbanism-cities-and-the-pattern-of-urban-life.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">99 - On the Planning of Cities/URBANISM - Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 06:48:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[URBAN - Density Machines - Comparative Urban Forms and Metabolisms]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="On the Planning of Cities" data-href="On the Planning of Cities" href="99-on-the-planning-of-cities/on-the-planning-of-cities.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">HOME</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="URBANISM - Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life" data-href="URBANISM - Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life" href="99-on-the-planning-of-cities/urbanism-cities-and-the-pattern-of-urban-life.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life</a><br>In earlier discussion, urbanism was described as a combination of sustained density and social heterogeneity, with cities functioning as specialised service hubs for the territories around them.<a data-footref="[inline0" href="#fn-1-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[1]</a> Modern cities continue to fit that broad description, but the ways in which density is arranged in space now diverge quite radically.<br>One prominent form is the large-footprint, low-average-density metropolis. Such cities spread across thousands of square kilometres, dominated by detached houses and car-based mobility. Their mean population densities, often around 1,500–2,000 people per square kilometre, align more closely with mid-sized North American cities than with the compact cores of older European or Asian urban centres.<a data-footref="[inline1" href="#fn-2-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[2]</a><br>However, this overall thinness conceals sharp local contrasts. If density is recalculated on a population-weighted basis – asking how dense the neighbourhoods are where people actually live – the pattern shifts. Recent analysis shows that one large coastal metropolis of this type has a population-weighted density almost double that of comparable cities, a consequence of rapid vertical construction along inner-city corridors and around public transport spines.<a data-footref="[inline2" href="#fn-3-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[3]</a>The outcome is a dual morphology, in which compact, highly specialised cores of apartments, offices and campuses are embedded within vast suburban bands where homes and workplaces are separated by long journeys. In these urban systems, the classic advantages of density are increasingly provided by technological means – lifts, high-capacity transit and digital networks – concentrated in a small number of nodes inside a very slack overall urban envelope.<br>From an economic standpoint, these cities usually concentrate advanced services such as finance, higher education, law and design, logistics and corporate management. Yet at the national scale, their economies may still depend heavily on exporting raw or only lightly processed commodities, reflected in relatively modest positions on indices like the Economic Complexity Index.<a data-footref="[inline3" href="#fn-4-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[4]</a> The cities therefore occupy highly specialised niches within a production system that, in structural terms, remains relatively simple.Set against this is the compressed, hyper-mixed metropolis. In this configuration, density is not confined to isolated pockets within sprawl; it is the prevailing condition. Land parcels are small, streets are tight, and buildings vertically layer residential, commercial and productive uses.A distinctive structure in this pattern is the narrow, elongated, multi-storey townhouse or “tube house”. Its ground level opens straight to the street as a shop, eatery or workshop; mezzanine levels are used for storage or light manufacturing; upper storeys accommodate multi-generational households. A single plot is thus able to host retail, production and domestic life at once.Here, density appears as spatial compression rather than as a mere side-effect of tall towers. Mixed use at the scale of individual buildings dissolves clear separations between dwelling, workplace and public realm. Everyday transaction costs are very low – one can work, shop and socialise in the same few metres – while the penalties of noise, pollution and crowding are equally concentrated.<br>In such settings, the classic traits of urbanity – heterogeneity, specialisation, intense interaction – are spread throughout the urban tissue instead of being packed into a small set of formal CBDs. Large manufacturing and assembly operations often sit nearby in industrial estates or export-processing zones, positioning the city as a hinge between inflowing foreign capital and local labour.<a data-footref="[inline4" href="#fn-5-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[5]</a>Both of these spatial logics function as density machines. Nodal sprawl demonstrates that a metropolis can maintain low headline densities while grafting on zones of classic high-density urban form, whereas compressed fabric illustrates that high densities and mixed uses can extend across whole districts using relatively straightforward construction methods. The distinction is crucial for everything that follows: it shapes mobility patterns, infrastructure finance, the distribution of density’s benefits, and the locations where environmental stress is most likely to build up.<br>Earlier chapters described historical cities as emerging from combinations of surplus (sufficient food and goods to support non-farmers) and pressure (crowding, environmental limits, elite extraction, warfare).<a data-footref="[inline5" href="#fn-6-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[6]</a> The same paired logic persists in contemporary systems, although it is channelled through different economic mechanisms.<br>In resource-rich economies, primary activities such as large-scale farming and mining generate substantial monetary surpluses while employing comparatively few people. Urbanisation under these conditions is driven by surplus gravity: a small number of highly productive sites – farms, mines, energy installations – produce export revenues, and major cities specialise in managing, insuring, financing and spending this income rather than manufacturing complex goods themselves.<a data-footref="[inline6" href="#fn-7-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[7]</a> Populations cluster in these cities because of a strong urban wage premium, where average earnings, especially in high-skill roles, rise more than proportionally with city size.<a data-footref="[inline7" href="#fn-8-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[8]</a> In effect, cities operate as consumption and command nodes for a hinterland that carries out most of the physical production.In these cases, the surplus underpinning urban growth is often physically generated far away – in mines, fields or offshore installations – but circulates through CBDs and affluent suburbs as salaries, service contracts and property booms.<br>In densely populated agrarian regions undergoing industrialisation, the dynamics are different again. Here, crowding-pressure in rural areas intersects with industrial pull around the metropolitan fringe. Historically cultivated regions with limited arable land and high rural densities experience shrinking farm plots and job losses as agriculture mechanises.<a data-footref="[inline8" href="#fn-9-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[9]</a> Simultaneously, foreign and domestic investors establish industrial zones and export-processing zones on city edges.<a data-footref="[inline9" href="#fn-10-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[10]</a><br>Peri-urban belts thus become the main arenas of transformation. Farmland is compulsorily acquired and reclassified either for “new urban areas” – dense residential and commercial complexes – or for industrial parks. Farmers receive compensation but lose their land base and are effectively propelled into urban labour markets.<a data-footref="[inline10" href="#fn-11-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[11]</a><br>In one capital-region example, roughly 150 such new urban projects had been launched by the mid-2010s, mostly 5–12 kilometres from the historic core, dramatically altering land-use patterns.<a data-footref="[inline11" href="#fn-12-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[12]</a> This is urbanisation as accumulation by dispossession: state agencies and capital investors gain strategic sites, while rural households absorb the disruption.One pathway, then, concentrates surplus generated in distant locations; the other turns surplus rural labour into industrial output. Both ultimately give rise to large, diverse cities, but they imprint very different political and social signatures on who moves, on what terms, and with what leverage.Urban life at scale depends on mechanisms for coordination: rules that determine who may live where, how land is held, what can be built, and how infrastructure is paid for. The specific “institutional technologies” that perform this coordination vary widely.<br>Some systems rely strongly on status distinctions to regulate urban membership. Household registration regimes function as internal passport systems, differentiating long-term, fully recognised urban residents from temporary or migrant populations.<a data-footref="[inline12" href="#fn-13-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[13]</a> Under these arrangements, entitlements to public schooling, healthcare, social protection or even basic utilities may hinge on registration status. Migrants lacking complete documentation commonly pay higher effective prices for water and electricity via landlords, reside in dense boarding houses near factories, and encounter obstacles when trying to enrol their children in local public schools or to access formal welfare programs.<a data-footref="[inline13" href="#fn-14-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[14]</a><br>The result is a dual urbanism: a formal city of residents with rights and a shadow city of workers whose labour is welcomed but whose claims on services are restricted. This structure effectively underwrites industrial urban expansion by shifting part of the cost of social reproduction back onto village-based support networks.<a data-footref="[inline14" href="#fn-15-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[15]</a><br>Land institutions lock in these patterns. Where land is nominally owned by “the people” and administered by the state, individuals and firms hold land use rights rather than outright freehold. These rights, recorded in Land Use Rights Certificates (LURCs), can be transferred or mortgaged, enabling land to behave within a quasi-market.<a data-footref="[inline15" href="#fn-16-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[16]</a> High rates of LURC issuance in urban areas – often covering more than 90% of residential plots – permit rapid formalisation and financialisation of land.<a data-footref="[inline16" href="#fn-17-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[17]</a> At the same time, broad state powers to reclaim land for “socio-economic development” make sweeping peri-urban land conversions possible, with limited avenues of appeal for those displaced.<a data-footref="[inline17" href="#fn-18-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[18]</a><br>By contrast, other systems rely more on rule-based markets. Land is generally held as freehold under register-based title systems that confer strong, court-enforceable rights on owners. Urban form is shaped by detailed zoning plans and building codes that prescribe permissible uses, heights, densities and design standards for each parcel. Development approval processes in these settings can be elaborate, but they often yield high scores on metrics such as the Building Quality Control Index, signalling a strong emphasis on structural safety and regulatory oversight.<a data-footref="[inline18" href="#fn-19-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[19]</a> This framework protects people and property but reduces the speed and flexibility of change; even modest incremental densification, such as adding extra storeys to existing houses, can be tightly constrained.<br>Finance in such systems is mediated through fiscal federalism. Local governments may rely primarily on property rates and limited fees, while state or provincial tiers fund major transport and social infrastructure using more volatile revenue streams such as transaction-based property taxes and payroll taxes. To meet the demands of fast-growing metropolitan populations, some state-level authorities have accumulated very large debts to build metro networks, tunnels and highways.<a data-footref="[inline19" href="#fn-20-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[20]</a> Here, the friction of urbanisation is expressed less as formal exclusion and more as slow, costly provision of housing and infrastructure.Status-based and zoning-based arrangements are, in effect, two different toolkits for solving the same underlying problem: determining who counts as belonging, who is allowed to build, and who finances what. The contrast matters for how easily migrants settle, how land is priced, and how rapidly cities can respond to shifting densities.<br>Earlier work in this series examined evidence that as settlements expand, many outputs – from wealth to innovation and infrastructure – do not simply scale in direct proportion to population but instead show superlinear or sublinear patterns.<a data-footref="[inline20" href="#fn-21-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[21]</a> Modern cities follow similar scaling laws, but what actually grows faster or slower than population depends heavily on the economic base.<br>In wealthy, service-heavy cities, the clearest increasing returns appear in information-intensive sectors. As employment density rises, productivity in finance, technology, professional services and other knowledge-rich industries tends to grow even faster.<a data-footref="[inline21" href="#fn-22-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[22]</a> The urban wage premium in these environments is strong but uneven: studies suggest that as city size increases, the earnings of already well-paid workers rise more steeply than those of lower-paid groups.<a data-footref="[inline22" href="#fn-23-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[23]</a> Much of the superlinear scaling of income is therefore captured at the top of the distribution.<br>In countries where a large slice of GDP still comes from non-urban sectors such as mining or large-scale agriculture, the relationship between city size and overall national output can be weaker. Growing metropolitan areas may function more as systems for managing and distributing wealth created elsewhere than as engines for developing new, complex export industries.<a data-footref="[inline23" href="#fn-24-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[24]</a><br>In industrialising economies, by contrast, increasing returns are often most visible in manufacturing and allied activities. Firms clustered in dense industrial corridors benefit from shared suppliers and logistics, thick labour markets with specialised skills, and knowledge spillovers about processes and technologies. Empirical work in one such context shows that private and foreign-owned firms in large urban regions enjoy substantial productivity gains from proximity to other firms (localisation economies), whereas state-owned enterprises display much weaker links between city size and performance, implying that competitive pressure is crucial for agglomeration benefits to fully manifest.<a data-footref="[inline24" href="#fn-25-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[25]</a><br>Infrastructure, however, frequently scales only partially. Even if the total length of roads or pipes increases sublinearly with population, rapid growth can still overrun capacity, producing chronic congestion and overload. The theoretical efficiencies of agglomeration arrive on the ground as packed buses and traffic jams rather than as carefully optimised networks.<a data-footref="[inline25" href="#fn-26-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[26]</a>Summarising, service-dominated cities tend to super-scale intangible outputs – ideas, transactions, sophisticated services – and funnel a disproportionate share of the gains to higher-income workers, while production-dominated cities tend to super-scale tangible outputs – manufactured goods and associated wages – but often struggle to keep infrastructure abreast of growth. Both cases support the general observation that larger cities usually achieve “more per person”; they simply diverge in what “more” consists of and in who gains most.<br>Earlier analysis argued that cities almost invariably distribute the benefits of density unevenly, whether in ancient Mesoamerica or in contemporary metropolises.<a data-footref="[inline26" href="#fn-27-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[27]</a> Present-day evidence supports this view but highlights different mechanisms.<br>In large, low-density, car-dependent cities, inequality is strongly spatially organised. Measures of income segregation such as the Duncan Index and entropy-based indicators show marked clustering of high-income households in particular sectors – often along waterfronts, favoured inner suburbs or well-serviced transport corridors – and concentration of lower-income households in outlying or poorly connected areas.<a data-footref="[inline27" href="#fn-28-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[28]</a> Housing prices, commuting times and school zones combine into what residents sometimes call a “latte line”: a loose internal border separating high-amenity, high-access districts from zones where housing is more affordable but commutes are longer and services thinner.<a data-footref="[inline28" href="#fn-29-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[29]</a><br>Long-term studies suggest that some cities of this type still retain pockets of social mixing, yet self-segregation by the affluent – clustering into a relatively small set of high-status suburbs – is hardening over time.<a data-footref="[inline29" href="#fn-30-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[30]</a> The costs of density – tolls and congestion, heat exposure, limited job access – fall disproportionately on a commuting service workforce that sustains the functioning of inner-city economies.<br>In dense, industrialising cities with status-based registration regimes, inequality acquires extra dimensions. Income disparities are widening, with national Gini coefficients in some cases rising into the 0.37–0.42 range as growth proceeds.<a data-footref="[inline30" href="#fn-31-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[31]</a> However, legal status and access to public services can matter as much as, or more than, income levels. Migrants who are unregistered or only temporarily registered and employed in factories often live in makeshift or substandard housing near industrial areas, pay more for basic utilities than fully registered neighbours, and lack secure access to schools and healthcare for their families.<a data-footref="[inline31" href="#fn-32-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[32]</a><br>At the same time, peri-urban land conversion and speculative real estate projects channel substantial unearned windfall gains to actors with influence over planning and land allocation. The built environment exhibits stark contrasts: luxury towers overlooking informal settlements, and gated enclaves positioned next to self-built neighbourhoods.<a data-footref="[inline32" href="#fn-33-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[33]</a> Patterns of occupational segregation, including differences in men’s and women’s access to formal employment, add a further layer to unequal outcomes from urbanisation.<a data-footref="[inline33" href="#fn-34-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[34]</a>In market-dominated systems, then, inequality is produced primarily through housing markets and transport networks: the critical question is who can afford proximity to what. In status-structured systems, inequality emerges from the combined effects of administrative categories and markets: where one is registered can be as consequential as what one earns. In both cases, the physical city renders inequality visible and durable.<br>Earlier chapters traced how many pre-modern cities functioned as demographic sinks, sustained by continuous migration despite high death rates, and how modern cities have increasingly shifted to fiscal constraints as the main brake on growth.<a data-footref="[inline34" href="#fn-35-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[35]</a> Contemporary examples confirm this transition while also revealing persistent biological pressures.<br>Some urban systems achieved basic control over waterborne diseases relatively early through heavy investment in piped water and sewerage. Others only crossed this threshold in recent decades. In parts of Southeast Asia, for instance, cholera and typhoid remained significant risks well into the late twentieth century, especially in river deltas and informal urban settlements.<a data-footref="[inline35" href="#fn-36-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[36]</a> Subsequent expansion of WASH (water, sanitation and hygiene) infrastructure and public health programs has sharply reduced incidence.<a data-footref="[inline36" href="#fn-37-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[37]</a><br>Nevertheless, vector-borne diseases such as dengue continue to exploit infrastructural and planning gaps, particularly in hot, flood-prone megacities. Hospitalisation records show strong associations between heatwaves, stagnant water and disease spikes, reminding planners that biological risks in cities have not disappeared.<a data-footref="[inline37" href="#fn-38-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[38]</a><br>Once basic public health is secured, the key constraint on urban density often becomes finance. In sprawling, infrastructure-hungry systems, governments must fund the retrofitting of mass transit, the renewal of ageing networks and the extension of services to low-density suburbs. State or provincial authorities frequently carry these obligations on their own balance sheets, generating high projected debt levels as they pay for railways, tunnels and major roads.<a data-footref="[inline38" href="#fn-39-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[39]</a> Questions about the sustainability of this borrowing, and about political willingness to adopt new revenue mechanisms such as value capture, move to the forefront.<br>In industrialising, centralised systems, the primary issue is often the allocation of fiscal power. Large cities that generate a substantial share of national tax receipts may keep only a small fraction for their own budgets, remitting the remainder to the central state. Retention ratios on the order of 18–23% have been reported for some major urban regions in recent years, even as their infrastructure requirements escalate.<a data-footref="[inline39" href="#fn-40-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[40]</a> One rapidly expanding metropolis, for example, recorded budget revenue above VNĐ 500 trillion (around US$19.6 billion) in 2024 yet still struggled to finance essential flood protection and metro projects.<a data-footref="[inline40" href="#fn-41-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[41]</a> In such circumstances, the limiting factor is not the creation of wealth but the capacity to capture and reinvest a sufficient share of it locally.Both types of city have largely escaped the archetypal “urban graveyard” condition, but they now confront two new ceilings: debt ceilings, where low-density systems must borrow heavily to align infrastructure with population, and retention ceilings, where high-density systems must negotiate for a greater share of the revenue they generate. In each case, the long-run sustainability of dense urban life depends as much on financial arrangements as on engineering solutions.Cities can also be understood as metabolic systems, converting flows of energy and materials into buildings, services and waste. Contemporary cases illustrate two contrasting but interconnected metabolic profiles.<br>Industrialising cities are typically in a phase of rapid stock accumulation. Their material footprint is dominated by inputs for construction: sand, gravel and crushed stone for concrete; cement and steel for structural frames; bricks and other masonry. Material flow analyses for one such economy show per capita material use rising from about 4 tonnes in 2000 to roughly 9–11 tonnes in the 2010s, with construction minerals making up a large share.<a data-footref="[inline41" href="#fn-42-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[42]</a> River sand mining to supply urban building booms has been linked to erosion and subsidence in key river basins.<a data-footref="[inline42" href="#fn-43-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[43]</a> In this mode, the city’s metabolism is one of mineralisation: deltas, hills and riverbeds are turned into high-rise housing, ring roads and industrial estates. The central metabolic dilemma is how to build enough, quickly enough, without degrading the resource base.<br>In mature, high-income, low-density systems, the emphasis shifts from accumulation to throughput. Per capita material footprints are higher overall and tilt towards fossil fuels for transport, heating and electricity; biomass and industrial products embodied in consumption; and maintenance materials for existing infrastructure.<a data-footref="[inline43" href="#fn-44-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[44]</a> Heavy car dependence and fossil-intensive electricity systems typically push per capita greenhouse gas emissions into the upper range of global figures, with values around 16 tonnes CO₂-equivalent per person reported for similar urban forms.<a data-footref="[inline44" href="#fn-45-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[45]</a> Water security is often maintained by energy-hungry technologies such as desalination and large-scale recycling, binding the urban metabolism closely to its energy system. Here, the main question is no longer “how do we build the city?” but “how do we decarbonise and reduce an already expanded urban metabolism without disrupting its services?”<br>Differences are also evident in water and waste cycles. In some industrialising contexts, access to improved drinking water sources has risen to around 98% of the population, yet long-term security is threatened by over-abstraction, pollution and saltwater intrusion in key aquifers and rivers.<a data-footref="[inline45" href="#fn-46-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[46]</a> Informal recyclers – waste pickers and small-scale brokers – recover significant shares of plastic, paper and metal waste, creating a bottom-up circular economy sustained by low wages and the high marginal value of recovered materials.<a data-footref="[inline46" href="#fn-47-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[47]</a>In many high-income systems, by contrast, water services are generally secure but energy-intensive, and waste streams are still largely linear: household rubbish is collected and transported to landfills or incinerators, with recycling rates rising only gradually. Policy discourse emphasises circularity, but everyday metabolism continues to assume that there is an “away” to which unwanted material can be sent.Construction-centred metabolisms thus convert large quantities of raw minerals into new urban stock at high speed, with major consequences for landscapes and future maintenance demands, whereas consumption-centred metabolisms consume large amounts of energy to sustain existing stock and lifestyles, concentrating impacts in the form of emissions rather than sand extraction. Both are tightly coupled to global climate and resource systems, and both must change if cities are to meet sustainability objectives.Taken together, these seven dimensions show that contemporary metropolises organised around resource exports and those built through industrial transition embody different responses to the same underlying urban challenge: how to house, move and coordinate millions of people within finite space. Resource-rich, low-density service cities demonstrate that modern urbanity can rest on nodal density inside expansive urban forms financed by exports generated elsewhere, but they face primarily fiscal challenges – paying for retrofits – and distributive ones – preventing the gains of high-end services from deepening spatial divides. High-density, industrialising cities reveal how crowding-pressure and foreign investment can combine to produce intense, hyper-mixed urban fabrics, but their central difficulties are institutional – reducing status-based exclusion – and metabolic – building infrastructure fast enough without exhausting land and water systems.As both groups of cities adjust, some degree of convergence is probable. Low-density systems are experimenting with greater inner-city and corridor densities and more mixed uses, while high-density systems are constructing formal metro networks, expanding welfare systems and tightening environmental regulation. Each is, in its own fashion, renegotiating a long-standing urban bargain: exchanging new sets of constraints and risks for new forms of connection and opportunity. The comparative perspective here implies that there is no single “end-state” of modern urbanity. Instead, there are families of solutions shaped by economic base, institutional design and ecological setting – all operating under shared physical laws of density, scaling and metabolism, yet each improvising its own local urban biology. <br>The Archaeology of Early Cities: “What Is the City but the People?” | Annual Reviews.<a href="#fnref-1-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Australian cities among the largest and least densely settled in the world | ArchitectureAu, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-2-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Trends in major city population density | Charting Transport, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-3-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Australia – The Atlas of Economic Complexity, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-4-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Economic Complexity Index | Wikipedia, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-5-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Emergence of Cities and States | Economic Prehistory.<a href="#fnref-6-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Australia – The Atlas of Economic Complexity.<a href="#fnref-7-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>(PDF) Urbanization Favors High Wage Earners | ResearchGate, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-8-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Urbanization and Post-Acquisition Livelihood in a Peri-Urban Context in Vietnam | MDPI, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-9-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Impact of Agglomeration Economies on Different Types of Firms in Vietnam | IDE, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-10-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Urbanization and Post-Acquisition Livelihood in a Peri-Urban Context in Vietnam | MDPI.<a href="#fnref-11-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The spatial mismatch between foreign direct investment and street networks: Evidence from Hanoi, Vietnam | ResearchGate, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-12-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Vietnam's household registration system | World Bank, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-13-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Social protection for rural-urban migrants in Vietnam | ILO, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-14-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Vietnam's household registration system | World Bank.<a href="#fnref-15-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Major Changes in the Regulations of Land Use Right Certificate and Their Impacts on Property Rights under the Land Law 2024 | ADK Vietnam Lawyers, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-16-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Major Changes in the Regulations of Land Use Right Certificate | ADK Vietnam Lawyers.<a href="#fnref-17-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Urbanization and Post-Acquisition Livelihood in a Peri-Urban Context in Vietnam | MDPI.<a href="#fnref-18-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Doing Business – DataBank | World Bank, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-19-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>State debt projections as cited in user materials.<a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-1" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">1</a><a href="#fnref-20-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Settlement Scaling and Increasing Returns in an Ancient Society | Santa Fe Institute.<a href="#fnref-21-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>(PDF) Evidence for localization and urbanization economies in urban scaling | ResearchGate, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-22-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>(PDF) Urbanization Favors High Wage Earners | ResearchGate, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-23-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>(PDF) Evidence for localization and urbanization economies in urban scaling | ResearchGate.<a href="#fnref-24-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Impact of Agglomeration Economies on Different Types of Firms in Vietnam | IDE.<a href="#fnref-25-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Vietnam – Hanoi city material flows | NERC, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-26-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Studies of Ancient Cities Suggest We Should Abandon Planning Elites | Smart Cities Dive, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-27-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Reflection of Income Segregation and Accessibility Cleavages in Sydney's House Prices | MDPI, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-28-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>The Reflection of Income Segregation and Accessibility Cleavages in Sydney's House Prices | MDPI.<a href="#fnref-29-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Spatial segregation and neighbourhood change | AHURI, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-30-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>LABOUR AND SOCIAL TRENDS IN VIET NAM 2021, OUTLOOK TO 2030 | ILO, accessed 30 November 2025; Towards more inclusive growth: OECD Economic Surveys: Viet Nam 2025 | OECD, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-31-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Social protection for rural-urban migrants in Vietnam | ILO.<a href="#fnref-32-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Urbanization and Post-Acquisition Livelihood in a Peri-Urban Context in Vietnam | MDPI.<a href="#fnref-33-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>LABOUR AND SOCIAL TRENDS IN VIET NAM 2021 | ILO.<a href="#fnref-34-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Toward a bioarchaeology of urbanization | ResearchGate; Population, Migration, and Generations in Urban Neighborhoods | Cleveland Fed.<a href="#fnref-35-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Vietnam's Water Resources: Current Status, Challenges, and Security Perspective | ResearchGate, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-36-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Water supply and sanitation in Vietnam | Wikipedia, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-37-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Vietnam's Water Resources | ResearchGate.<a href="#fnref-38-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>State debt projections as cited in user materials.<a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-2" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">2</a><a href="#fnref-39-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Towards more inclusive growth: OECD Economic Surveys: Viet Nam 2025 | OECD.<a href="#fnref-40-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>HCMC budget revenue figures as cited in user materials.<a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-3" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">3</a><a href="#fnref-41-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Viet Nam Resource Efficiency Policies | CSIRO Research, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-42-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Vietnam – Hanoi city material flows | NERC, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-43-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Cities and the New Climate Economy: The Transformative Role of Global Urban Growth | LSE, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-44-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Cities and the New Climate Economy | LSE.<a href="#fnref-45-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Water supply and sanitation in Vietnam | Wikipedia; Vietnam's Water Resources | ResearchGate.<a href="#fnref-46-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Market Study for Vietnam: PLASTICS CIRCULARITY OPPORTUNITIES AND BARRIERS | IFC, accessed 30 November 2025.<a href="#fnref-47-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a> <br>citation needed<a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-1" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩</a>
<br>citation needed<a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-2" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩</a>
<br>citation needed<a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-3" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩</a> ]]></description><link>99-on-the-planning-of-cities/urbanism-density-machines-comparative-urban-forms-and-metabolisms.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">99 - On the Planning of Cities/URBANISM - Density Machines - Comparative Urban Forms and Metabolisms.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 06:46:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[URBANISM - Urban Scaling Laws]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="On the Planning of Cities" data-href="On the Planning of Cities" href="99-on-the-planning-of-cities/on-the-planning-of-cities.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">HOME</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="URBANISM - Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life" data-href="URBANISM - Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life" href="99-on-the-planning-of-cities/urbanism-cities-and-the-pattern-of-urban-life.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life</a><br>Many features of cities obey simple scaling rules. Measure an urban quantity (GDP, patents, road length, crime, infrastructure) against population , and you often find a power law . The exponent is not a whim; it behaves like a system constant that discloses something fundamental about urban organisation. The striking point is recurrence: across nations and eras, the same families of exponents reappear, signalling persistent properties of human aggregation.{“Power-law” scaling of urban indicators with characteristic exponents}<a data-footref="[inline0" href="#fn-1-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[1]</a> {theoretical account of why such regularities arise}<a data-footref="[inline1" href="#fn-2-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[2]</a><br>The mechanism is agglomeration: cities deliberately compress distance among people and firms. Proximity multiplies encounters, shortens search, and produces nonlinear gains that dispersed settlement cannot match. From complexity science, cities are not equilibria but evolving, bottom-up “social reactors” whose macroscopic regularities emerge from countless local interactions. Features such as scaling, self-similarity, and far-from-equilibrium dynamics follow naturally from this view; in some subsystems (e.g., mobility networks), behaviour clusters near critical transitions where small perturbations can trigger large shifts.{Cities as evolving complex systems}<a data-footref="[inline2" href="#fn-3-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[3]</a> {critical-like behaviour in traffic networks}<a data-footref="[inline3" href="#fn-4-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[4]</a><br>One signature is superlinear scaling, . When population doubles, socio-economic outputs—income, GDP, patents—more than double. Typical exponents cluster around (often –). This is the quantitative fingerprint of dense urban form translating into accelerated knowledge production: proximity raises the frequency and productivity of interactions, especially for tacit know-how.{Empirical superlinear exponents}<a data-footref="[inline4" href="#fn-5-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[5]</a> {ancient settlements show same pattern}<a data-footref="[inline5" href="#fn-6-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[6]</a><br>The amplifier is neutral: beneficent and malign outputs scale alike. Creativity, R&amp;D, and high-skill services rise superlinearly—but so do certain crimes and social frictions. Crime indicators including homicide consistently exhibit across datasets.{Crime scaling}<a data-footref="[inline6" href="#fn-7-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[7]</a> Congestion delays also tend to scale superlinearly (often –), implying worse per-capita delay in larger cities, even as total productivity continues to grow faster.<br>By contrast, many infrastructural and material needs show sublinear scaling, . Double the population and you need markedly less than double the physical network: roads, pipes, and cables grow with –. This is the mathematics of economies of scale in space: denser arrangement allows shared facilities and shorter connections.{Sublinear infrastructure exponents}<a data-footref="[inline7" href="#fn-8-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[8]</a><br>These internal laws are more robust than external rank-size patterns like Zipf’s law. Zipf often approximates large U.S. cities but fails elsewhere and is highly sensitive to definitional choices. Scaling relations , by contrast, reappear reliably when boundaries are defined consistently.{Limits of Zipf}<a data-footref="[inline8" href="#fn-9-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[9]</a><br>Urban form itself is fractal. Self-similar patterns repeat from street blocks to metro regions, a natural outcome of decentralised, incremental growth that maximises interface in limited area. The fractal dimension of built-up fabric almost always lies between and : values near indicate compact, space-filling cities; lower values mark more dispersed, void-laden forms.{Fractal cities}<a data-footref="[inline9" href="#fn-10-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[10]</a><br>City boundaries also display fractality. Depending on method, perimeter-based dimensions typically lie around –, reflecting irregular, jagged edges that increase the interface between city and hinterland.{Fractal perimeter metrics}<a data-footref="[inline10" href="#fn-11-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[11]</a><br>Street networks blend grid-like redundancy with tree-like hierarchy. This hybrid reliably appears worldwide because it solves the universal problem of linking specialised local areas to high-capacity citywide circulation.{Street-network structure}<a data-footref="[inline11" href="#fn-12-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[12]</a><br>Within these networks, centrality reveals the structural skeleton that organises flows of people and goods. Multiple Centrality Assessment identifies key streets and nodes across both self-organised and planned cities. Scaling relations linking population to central civic areas hold in ancient and modern systems alike, including Roman settlements.{Centrality diagnostics}<a data-footref="[inline12" href="#fn-13-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[13]</a> {Roman civic-space scaling}<a data-footref="[inline13" href="#fn-14-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[14]</a><br>Urbanity—the lived social system—emerges from these physical and mathematical constraints. Its functional constant is specialisation: cities concentrate the non-agricultural economy because tacit-knowledge, interaction-heavy tasks gain most from proximity. Central Place Theory explains how cities form hierarchies based on service thresholds.{Skill complementarity in cities}<a data-footref="[inline14" href="#fn-15-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[15]</a> {Central Place Theory}<a data-footref="[inline15" href="#fn-16-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[16]</a><br>Population size and density correlate with social complexity: deeper division of labour, finer occupational niches. Cities especially reward interactive occupations, which scale faster in metropolitan contexts across long historical windows.{Interactive work premium}<a data-footref="[inline16" href="#fn-17-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[17]</a><br>With specialisation comes heterogeneity. Large cities support more varied industries, subcultures, lifeways, and political attitudes. Diversity widens the repertoire of recombinable ideas, underpinning innovation and resilience.{Urban diversity}<a data-footref="[inline17" href="#fn-18-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[18]</a><br>In such environments, weak ties—many low-intensity links—become economically potent, ferrying specialised information across the system. Digital platforms overlay “digitised social capital” through rating systems and verified identities, enabling trust among strangers.{Weak ties}<a data-footref="[inline18" href="#fn-19-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[19]</a> {Reputation systems}<a data-footref="[inline19" href="#fn-20-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[20]</a><br>Telecommunication data show that urban residents exhibit more complex mobility, more diverse contact networks, and greater reliance on formal systems for specialised services.{Mobility from phone data}<a data-footref="[inline20" href="#fn-21-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[21]</a><br>Taken together, these findings reveal an integrated system. Urbanism—dense, fractal form and hybrid networks—enables urbanity—non-agricultural specialisation, heterogeneity, segmented ties—and urbanisation then proceeds under scaling laws: superlinear socio-economic exponents (typically –), superlinear frictions, and sublinear infrastructures (typically –). The fractal dimension of built form (with ) and the dominance of non-farm, interaction-heavy work define the functional threshold of urban life.{Synthesis of constraints}<a data-footref="[inline21" href="#fn-22-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[22]</a><br>These are constraints within which planning and policy must work. Strategies that deny the superlinear benefits of density or the sublinear economy of infrastructure court predictable failure because they conflict with the empirical “social physics” of cities.{Policy relevance and temporal stability}<a data-footref="[inline22" href="#fn-23-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[23]</a> <br>Bettencourt, L. M. A. et al. (2007) PNAS, 104(17), 7301–7306.<a href="#fnref-1-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Bettencourt, L. M. A. (2013) Science, 340, 1438–1441.<a href="#fnref-2-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Batty, M. (2013) The New Science of Cities. MIT Press.<a href="#fnref-3-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Li, D. et al. (2015) PNAS, 112(3), 669–672.<a href="#fnref-4-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Bettencourt, L. M. A. et al. (2007) PNAS, 104(17), 7301–7306.<a href="#fnref-5-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Ortman, S. G. et al. (2015) Science Advances, 1(1), e1400066.<a href="#fnref-6-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Alves, L. G. A. et al. (2013) PLOS ONE, 8(9), e73013.<a href="#fnref-7-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Samaniego, H. &amp; Moses, M. (2008) Journal of Transport and Land Use, 1(1), 21–39.<a href="#fnref-8-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Arcaute, E. et al. (2015) R. Soc. Open Sci., 2, 150691.<a href="#fnref-9-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Batty, M. &amp; Longley, P. (1994) Fractal Cities. Academic Press.<a href="#fnref-10-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Chen, Y. (2014) Fractals, 22(2), 1450007.<a href="#fnref-11-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Barthélemy, M. (2011) Physics Reports, 499, 1–101.<a href="#fnref-12-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Porta, S. et al. (2006) Environment and Planning B, 33, 705–725.<a href="#fnref-13-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Hanson, J. W. &amp; Ortman, S. G. (2017) Journal of Roman Archaeology, 30, 301–324.<a href="#fnref-14-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Glaeser, E. &amp; Resseger, M. (2010) Journal of Regional Science, 50, 221–244.<a href="#fnref-15-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Christaller, W. (1933/1966) Central Places in Southern Germany.<a href="#fnref-16-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Bacolod, M. et al. (2009) Review of Economics and Statistics, 91, 254–267.<a href="#fnref-17-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Fischer, C. S. (1975) AJS, 80, 1319–1341.<a href="#fnref-18-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Granovetter, M. (1973) AJS, 78, 1360–1380.<a href="#fnref-19-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Resnick, P. &amp; Zeckhauser, R. (2002) in Economics of the Internet.<a href="#fnref-20-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>González, M. C. et al. (2008) Nature, 453, 779–782.<a href="#fnref-21-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Pumain, D. et al. (2006) Cybergeo, paper 2519.<a href="#fnref-22-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Bettencourt, L. M. A. (2020) Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B, 375, 20190376.<a href="#fnref-23-462deb3ab811bdd5" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
]]></description><link>99-on-the-planning-of-cities/urbanism-urban-scaling-laws.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">99 - On the Planning of Cities/URBANISM - Urban Scaling Laws.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[On the Planning of Cities]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img alt="FIGURE - Urbanism As A Coupled System.png" src="99-on-the-planning-of-cities/illustrations/figure-urbanism-as-a-coupled-system.png" target="_self">
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="URBANISM - Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life" data-href="URBANISM - Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life" href="99-on-the-planning-of-cities/urbanism-cities-and-the-pattern-of-urban-life.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life</a>
]]></description><link>99-on-the-planning-of-cities/on-the-planning-of-cities.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">99 - On the Planning of Cities/On the Planning of Cities.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[FIGURE - Urbanism As A Coupled System]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="99-on-the-planning-of-cities/illustrations/figure-urbanism-as-a-coupled-system.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>99-on-the-planning-of-cities/illustrations/figure-urbanism-as-a-coupled-system.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">99 - On the Planning of Cities/Illustrations/FIGURE - Urbanism As A Coupled System.png</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 10:09:10 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>