<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Untitled RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>site-lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Untitled RSS Feed</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 07:09:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="site-lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 07:09:15 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[URBANISM - Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="On the Planning of Cities" data-href="On the Planning of Cities" href="99-on-the-planning-of-cities/on-the-planning-of-cities.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">HOME</a>Urbanism is about living in close proximity and the consequences this has for us.What, in truth, is a city?Urbanism starts from a simple decision: people opt to live side by side, packed into large, dense, long-lasting clusters made up mostly of strangers.<br>A well-known sociological definition portrays a city as “a relatively large, dense, and permanent settlement of socially heterogeneous individuals”.<a data-footref="[inline0" href="#fn-1-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[1]</a> Put bluntly, it means many people crammed into a single location, mostly unrelated to one another, sharing life side by side over long periods.<br>There is also a second, equally important way to think about a city. Rather than focusing solely on who happens to live within its bounds, we can focus on what it does for the wider region around it. Seen this way, a city is a settlement that carries out specialised functions — administration, storage, trade, craft production, religious and political leadership — on behalf of a much larger surrounding countryside.<a data-footref="[inline1" href="#fn-2-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[2]</a> It acts as a service node for farms, villages, and smaller towns.Urbanism, as an idea, lies at the junction of these two perspectives. It is about more than simply having “big settlements”. It is a particular way of organising human life: density plus specialisation. It means many people in one place, doing different kinds of work, linked through institutions that extend beyond the city walls.Once this pattern takes hold, it alters almost everything: how food is produced, how power is exercised, how diseases spread, how wealth builds up, and how we think about time, identity, and the future. Urbanism is not merely scenery in the background. It is one of humanity’s primary technologies for reorganising society.The first cities can be seen as slow, long-running experiments in living at high density.<br>The earliest well-documented urban system emerges in southern Mesopotamia, in what archaeologists refer to as the Uruk Period, roughly 4200–3100 BCE.<a data-footref="[inline2" href="#fn-3-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[3]</a> Cities such as Ur did not erupt into existence overnight. The shift from villages to fully urban societies unfolded over roughly 500–700 years.<a data-footref="[inline3" href="#fn-4-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[4]</a> That represents many generations of people learning how to inhabit new kinds of spaces under new rules.<br>Archaeological surveys indicate that early Mesopotamian cities typically expanded by spreading out from an older village core, maintaining roughly similar densities as they grew.<a data-footref="[inline4" href="#fn-5-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[5]</a> Ur itself covered about 10 hectares around 3800 BCE and grew to roughly 15 hectares by about 3200 BCE.<a data-footref="[inline5" href="#fn-6-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[6]</a> By modern standards that may seem modest, but in its own time it marked a dramatic concentration of people, resources, and decision-making.<br>Mesopotamia is just one case among many. Cities arose independently in other regions — the Indus Valley, northern China, Mesoamerica, the Andes — following different local pathways but converging on strikingly similar outcomes: dense populations, long-distance networks, specialised labour, and formal institutions.<a data-footref="[inline6" href="#fn-7-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[7]</a><br>The physical constraints of each region left a deep imprint on its urban form. In Mesopotamia, cities were strung along rivers and canals that enabled bulk transport of grain, building materials, and goods.<a data-footref="[inline7" href="#fn-8-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[8]</a> In central Mexico, cities such as Teotihuacan lacked large domestic animals for carrying loads and had no convenient river routes for boats. They therefore had to construct entire urban and imperial systems around human porters and walking.<a data-footref="[inline8" href="#fn-9-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[9]</a> That logistical difference helped shape street plans, storage systems, and even the practical upper limits of city size.So from the outset, urbanism is not a single, uniform phenomenon. It is a family of solutions to a common problem: how to concentrate people and power in a given landscape, using whatever transport, crops, and animals happen to be available.Why, then, do cities form at all, and what do surplus, safety, and pressure have to do with it?If for most of history the majority of people were farmers, why did some communities decide to crowd into places where most residents did not grow their own food?The short answer is: surplus. The longer answer is: surplus combined with pressure.<br>First, consider surplus. Large-scale urban life is impossible without a farming system that routinely produces more food than local farmers themselves consume, and that can channel that surplus into town. In the ancient Near East, the domestication of cereals such as wheat and barley, along with herd animals, generated this extra margin. It allowed a portion of the population to be released from direct food production and to specialise in crafts, administration, religious roles, and trade.<a data-footref="[inline9" href="#fn-10-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[10]</a><br>Urbanisation, in turn, feeds back into the countryside. As people relocate into cities, fewer farmers remain in rural areas; the land they leave tends to be consolidated into larger farms.<a data-footref="[inline10" href="#fn-11-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[11]</a> In many settings, larger farm sizes are associated with higher productivity per worker. Urban demand also pushes farmers towards more intensive cultivation: manuring fields more heavily and concentrating on high-yield, high-demand crops, such as the barley used for beer in ancient Mesopotamian cities.<a data-footref="[inline11" href="#fn-12-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[12]</a> Urbanism, seen this way, is a system-wide optimisation: it rearranges labour so that both fields and workshops are used more intensively.Surplus on its own does not explain why people submit to new forms of rule or accept the risks that come with dense living. Here, historians and economists propose several mechanisms.<br>In one account, elites gradually tighten their grip on the best farmland as population grows and technology advances. As common fields contract and wages fall, ordinary farmers are nudged or driven into non-farm work in emerging towns and cities — especially when openings in urban manufacturing look more appealing than deteriorating conditions in the countryside.<a data-footref="[inline12" href="#fn-13-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[13]</a><br>In another account, warfare among elites is the main engine. When conflict over land and tribute intensifies, retreating behind city walls becomes a rational act of self-defence. Populations cluster in fortified locations, both to shield themselves and to underpin elite military ventures. Victorious warlords then use these dense centres as bases for territorial expansion.<a data-footref="[inline13" href="#fn-14-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[14]</a><br>A third pathway emphasises the environment. When climate or geography funnels people into narrow zones — river valleys, oases, coastal plains — populations become denser almost by compulsion. Land grows more valuable, wages for ordinary workers decline, and elites who control access to these safe or fertile zones gain leverage. Under these squeezed conditions, urbanisation and state formation follow.<a data-footref="[inline14" href="#fn-15-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[15]</a>Across these accounts, one idea recurs: cities arise when the organisational benefits of crowding — for farming, warfare, or resource control — exceed the obvious discomforts of living packed together.Cities can also be understood as dense machines for running institutions.Once dense, diverse populations are concentrated in one place, new kinds of rules, records, rituals, and buildings are needed to keep everything functioning. This is the institutional dimension of urbanism.<br>Early cities functioned as “clearing houses” for resources.<a data-footref="[inline15" href="#fn-16-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[16]</a> Grain, textiles, tribute, and craft goods were brought into central storehouses, redistributed to workers, soldiers, and priests, and channelled into monuments and public works. The closer workshops, offices, and storage rooms sat to one another, the lower the logistical costs: information and goods could move quickly through a compact space.<br>To manage all this, societies had to invent or greatly expand administrative tools: accounting systems, legal codes, standardised weights and measures, professional scribes, permanent offices, layered hierarchies. Social complexity increased through diversification (more specialised roles), connectivity (denser ties between them), and standardisation (shared rules and categories).<a data-footref="[inline16" href="#fn-17-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[17]</a><br>Urban layouts mirrored these changes. In Mesopotamia, temple and palace complexes dominated city centres, physically embodying the union of religious, economic, and political authority.<a data-footref="[inline17" href="#fn-18-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[18]</a> In many settings, priest-kings or other elites legitimised their power through religious narratives and rituals. Early sociologists, and later Max Weber, argued that cities are moulded not only by material needs but also by worldviews: ideas about gods, justice, purity, and order seep into street plans and law codes.<a data-footref="[inline18" href="#fn-19-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[19]</a>Urbanism, then, is not simply about physical proximity. It concerns new forms of coordination — bureaucratic, religious, legal — that only make sense when many thousands of people must share space and resources day after day.High density brings greater output, but that extra production is shared very unevenly.<br>Recent work on both ancient and modern cities highlights a key point: urban systems tend to produce more than the sum of their parts. The larger and denser a settlement becomes, the more interactions each person experiences, and the more ideas, deals, and collaborations can be generated per head. Statistically, socio-economic output increases faster than population size.<a data-footref="[inline19" href="#fn-20-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[20]</a><br>Researchers refer to this as “increasing returns to scale”. In mathematical models, it appears as a scaling exponent greater than one: double the population and you obtain more than double the output.<a data-footref="[inline20" href="#fn-21-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[21]</a> This pattern surfaces not only in modern GDP statistics but also in archaeological proxies.<br>In ancient cities of the Basin of Mexico, the volume of public monuments — pyramids, plazas, ceremonial platforms — increases superlinearly with estimated population size. The bigger the city, the more monument-building per person it was able to sustain.<a data-footref="[inline21" href="#fn-22-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[22]</a> Household sizes, inferred from the area of house mounds, also tend to be larger in more populous settlements, suggesting higher average productivity or access to resources for residents of big cities.<a data-footref="[inline22" href="#fn-23-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[23]</a><br>Yet these gains are not shared evenly. The same studies reveal substantial inequality in how built space is distributed. In the pre-Hispanic Basin of Mexico, the top 10 percent of households ended up occupying 40–50 percent of total housing area.<a data-footref="[inline23" href="#fn-24-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[24]</a> That skewed pattern is the physical imprint of unequal access to the benefits of density.Put simply, cities are engines that convert dense social networks into extra output. But they also direct a disproportionate share of that extra output to people already well positioned inside those networks — politically, economically, or spatially.High productivity has long come with a biological price tag: the urban graveyard.If cities are so productive, why were they, for much of history, such hostile places for human bodies?<br>Bioarchaeology, the study of human remains in archaeological contexts, presents a stark picture. Early and medieval cities frequently endured very high mortality rates. Diseases spread rapidly in crowded streets, water sources became contaminated, and waste disposal was poor. The so-called “Urban Graveyard Effect” captures this reality: cities tended to function as demographic sinks, where deaths outnumbered births over the long term.<a data-footref="[inline24" href="#fn-25-2c41142a6beb72d0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[25]</a>]]></description><link>urbanism-cities-and-the-pattern-of-urban-life.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">99 - On the Planning of Cities/URBANISM - Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 06:48:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[On the Planning of Cities]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img alt="FIGURE - Urbanism As A Coupled System.png" src="99-on-the-planning-of-cities/illustrations/figure-urbanism-as-a-coupled-system.png" target="_self">
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="URBANISM - Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life" data-href="URBANISM - Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life" href="99-on-the-planning-of-cities/urbanism-cities-and-the-pattern-of-urban-life.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Cities and the Pattern of Urban Life</a>
]]></description><link>99-on-the-planning-of-cities/on-the-planning-of-cities.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">99 - On the Planning of Cities/On the Planning of Cities.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[FIGURE - Urbanism As A Coupled System]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="99-on-the-planning-of-cities/illustrations/figure-urbanism-as-a-coupled-system.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>99-on-the-planning-of-cities/illustrations/figure-urbanism-as-a-coupled-system.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">99 - On the Planning of Cities/Illustrations/FIGURE - Urbanism As A Coupled System.png</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 10:09:10 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>